Guide to the Imperial Portrait Photograph File [1856-1870] PR 210
New York University Libraries, Publisher
- Series IV: Portraits by Jeremiah Gurney
  Jeremiah Gurney (1812-1895) was one of New York's finest portrait photographers, and is known primarily for his daguerrean work. His carte de visite and cabinet-format portraits are not uncommon in public and private collections, but his Imperial format portraits are rare. Emily Ward's portrait measures 19 by 16-1/4 inches and is on its original studio mount marked by Gurney in two places: an oval blind stamp in the front lower margin and a paper label on the verso; both give the studio's address as 707 Broadway, the location of Gurney's studio from 1858 through 1868. The group portrait is not marked, but is attributed to Gurney based on the quality of the photograph, and on the distinctive carpet showing in the image, which is also seen in marked Gurney carte de visite photographs (for examples, see album no. 415 in PR 002, the Album File, The House of Bishops of the Protestant Episcopal Church of the United States Photographed from life during the Triennial Convention by J. Gurney & Son (New York: T. Porter Shaw, 1862.) The family inscription on the verso of the mount suggests the photographer was William Kurtz (1834-1904), but he is not listed in the New York City directories until 1865.
  - Parmly and Ward family members, [1862 Apr. 11]; salted paper photograph; 13 x 14 3/4 in. (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Ward, Emily (ca. 1832-1877), [1858]; salted paper photograph; See: Oversize folder 28; 19 x 16 1/4 in.
- Series V: Portraits by Unidentified Photographers
  Series V. Portraits by Unidentified Photographers contains three portraits, two of which are identified men. They are Colonel John Jacob Astor III (1822-1890) and William Pitt Fessenden (1806-1869); both may be later enlargements from negatives made in the mid-1860s but are included in this collection based on their sheet size and vintage. The third portrait is of an unidentified man with an American flag, and features drapery and a classical column often seen in Mathew Brady portraits. Photographs are arranged alphabetically by sitter.
  - Astor III, John Jacob, Colonel (1822-1890), undated; albumen photograph; 18 3/8 x 14 3/4 in. (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Fessenden, William Pitt (1806-1869), undated; albumen photograph; 20 1/4 x 15 in. (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Unidentified man with American flag, undated; salted paper photograph; 18 3/8 x 14 3/4 in. (Box 5, Folder 27)
- Oversize Material
  Oversize material is filed in one flat folder housed in a map case drawer.
  - From Series I. Portraits by Mathew Brady
    - Scott, Winfield (1786-1866), undated; retouched salted paper photograph on engraved studio mount; 18 1/2 x 15 1/2 in. (Folder 28)
  - From Series III. Portrait by Charles Fredricks
    - Webb, James Watson (1802-1884), 1858; retouched salted paper photograph; 17 x 14 1/4 in. (Folder 28)
  - From Series IV. Portraits by Jeremiah Gurney
    - Ward, Emily (ca. 1837-1877), [1858]; salted paper photograph; 19 x 16 1/4 in. (Folder 28)
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Additional portraits of people in this collection, and additional work by the photographers represented here, can be found in the Print Room's Album File (PR 002), Carte de Visite File (PR 011), Cased Photograph File (PR 012), Mathew B. Brady Studio Portrait Photograph Collection (PR 085), Portrait File (PR 052), and Civil War Photograph File (PR 164).